Guide to the Meyer Schapiro Collection,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series III: Professional Papers, 1929-1990
  - Subseries: III.3: Lectures, 1930s-1980s
    - Sub-Subseries: III.3.4: 1960s
      - Beatus manuscripts of the apocalypse -- New York Studio School of Drawing, Painting and Sculpture -- Annotated transcripts, 1969 May 2 (Box 213, Folder 7 to 8)
        - Baudelaire between the imaginary and the real -- Queens College (New York, N.Y.)
          Sound recordings of this lecture can be found in Series VII, Subseries VII.2)
        - Annotated transcript, 1969 April 22 (Box 213, Folder 9)
        - Annotated typescript, 1969 April 22 (Box 213, Folder 10)
        - Annotated outlines and notes, 1969 April 22 (Box 213, Folder 11)
      - The present state of art history -- Queens College (New York, N.Y.) -- Annotated outlines, transcript, and notes, 1969 June 5 (Box 213, Folder 12)
        (Lecture title is derived from the sound recording found in Series VII, Subseries VII.2)
      - E.A. (Elias Avery) Lowe memorial -- Institute for Advanced Study (Princeton, N.J.)
        (Material relates to Schapiro's eulogy at the memorial. Sound recordings of this lecture can be found in Series VII, Subseries VII.2)
        - Annotated outline, typescripts, notes, and invitations, 1969 October 15 (Box 213, Folder 13)
        - Annotated transcript, 1969 October 15 (Box 213, Folder 14)
    - Sub-Subseries: III.3.5: 1970s
      - An experiment in the coherence of forms -- Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum -- Annotated transcript, correspondence, and slides, circa 1970s (Box 213, Folder 15)
      - Men with ideas: Alexander, Daedalus, Icarus: legends of the invention of flying -- Carnegie Institute of Technology
        - Annotated and corrected transcripts, 1971 January 27 (Box 213, Folder 16)
          (Accompanied by Schapiro's 1992 editorial notes for potential publication)
        - Drafts and notes, 1971 January 27 (Box 213, Folder 17)
          (Early drafts of lecture notes from other lectures pertaining to flight)
        - Research file, 1971 January (Box 214, Folder 1)
        - Research file, 1971 January (Box 214, Folder 2)
          (Includes annotated outline and research notes on "legends of flight")
        - Reproductions, 1971 January (Box 214, Folder 3)
      - Ornament and painting -- New York Studio School of Drawing, Painting and Sculpture
        - Annotated transcript, 1971 April 23 (Box 214, Folder 4)
          (Accompanied by research notes, alternate drafts, and editorial notes regarding reconstruction of text for potential publication by Lillian Milgram Schapiro)
        - Annotated transcript, 1978 April 23 (Box 214, Folder 5)
          (Photocopy of transcript with editorial notes created by Miriam Bunim in 1986)
        - Typescript, 1971 April 23 (Box 214, Folder 6)
          (Typescript created in 1998 following the 1971 annotated transcript. Accompanied by editorial notes by Lillian Milgram Schapiro)
        - Slide list and notes, 1971 (Box 214, Folder 7)
        - Reproductions, 1971, (3 Folders) (Box 214, Folder 8 to 10)
        - Editorial files, 1980s-1990s (Box 214, Folder 11 to 13)
          (Files contain notes, correspondence, and drafts by Lillian Milgram Schapiro and Robin Sands relating to editing lecture content)
      - Mondrian's forms and their relation to preceding styles of representation -- Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum
        - Transcripts, 1971 October 9 (Box 215, Folder 1)
        - Annotated transcripts, 1971 October 9 (Box 215, Folder 2)
        - Research notes, 1971 October 9, (5 Folders) (Box 215, Folder 3 to 7)
      - Institutions for a post-technological society: the Universitas Project -- Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.) -- Notes, correspondence, and press release, 1972 January 8-9 (Box 215, Folder 8)
        (Schapiro was a participant in the second working session. Notes are chiefly on Jean Baudrillard who participated in the same session)
      - Graphic analysis of structure -- University of Virginia
        - Annotated transcript, 1972 April 11 (Box 215, Folder 9)
          (Accompanied by editorial notes)
        - Annotated outline, 1972 April 11 (Box 215, Folder 10)
        - Slide lists, notes, and correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 215, Folder 11)
      - Alfred Barr eulogy -- Unidentified event -- Annotated outlines and notes, 1972 April (Box 215, Folder 12)
        (Lecture given at an awards ceremony honoring Barr)
      - Columbia speaks out on war! -- Typescript and broadside, 1972 May 18 (Box 215, Folder 13)
      - Romanesque architectural sculpture -- New College (Sarasota, Fla.) -- Annotated outlines and notes, 1973 January (Box 215, Folder 14)
      - Science and art -- Yeshiva University -- Annotated outline, 1973 March (Box 215, Folder 15)
      - An experiment with forms in art -- Columbia University -- Annotated transcript, 1973 April 2 (Box 215, Folder 16)
        (Lecture chiefly on Insular art. Accompanied by original outline, research files, clippings, press releases, and correspondence with faculty and students. Sound recordings of this lecture can be found in Series VII, Subseries VII.2)
      - The use of the Old Testament in the art of the middle ages -- Jewish Museum (New York, N.Y.) -- Transcript, notes, and slide list, 1973 October 22 (Box 215, Folder 17)
      - The south tower of the cathedral of Chartres -- Columbia University. School of Architecture
        - Annotated transcript, 1973 October 3 (Box 216, Folder 1)
        - Annotated pages, 1973 October 3 (Box 216, Folder 2)
        - Drafts, research notes, and slide lists, 1973 October 3 (Box 216, Folder 3)
      - The unity of Picasso's art -- Albright-Knox Art Gallery -- Annotated transcript, 1973 December 5 (Box 216, Folder 4)
        (Accompanied by list of illustrations to be used in a film of the lecture produced by Gittelman Film Associates for the Metropolitan Museum of Art Video Collection. Sound recordings of this lecture can be found in Series VII, Subseries VII.2)
      - Romanesque sculpture -- Collège de France -- Typescripts, broadsides, and invitations, 1974 May (Box 216, Folder 5)
        (In French. Lecture was originally given in English. Accompanied by research notes, slide lists, correspondence, and invitations)
      - Museums -- American Assembly -- Arden House (Harriman, N.Y.) -- Annotated outlines, notes, programs, and correspondence, 1974 November (Box 216, Folder 6)
        (Lecture was given at the forty-sixth annual American Assembly dedicated to art museums in America)
      - The study of art in the university -- Columbia University -- Annotated outlines, notes, and invitations, 1975 April 7 (Box 216, Folder 7)
        (Lecture given for the School of General Studies alumni)
      - Structuralism and art -- Columbia University -- Annotated outline, notes, and correspondence, 1976 December (Box 216, Folder 8)
        (Guest lecture at an anthropology colloquium taught by Paula G. Rubel)
      - Cézanne and the philosophers -- Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.)
      - Annotated transcripts, 1977 October 11, (2 Folders) (Box 216, Folder 9 to 10)
      - Research notes, 1977 October (Box 216, Folder 11)
        (Notes are chiefly from the 1950s and includes a summary and critique of Fritz Novotny)
      - Research notes, 1977 October (Box 216, Folder 12)
      - Research files, 1977 October, (2 Folders) (Box 216, Folder 13 to 14)
      - Editorial notes, 1990s (Box 216, Folder 15)
        (Notes created by Lillian Milgram Schapiro)
      - An experiment with the coherence of forms -- Wellesley College -- Slide lists and outlines, 1979 April (Box 217, Folder 1)
      - Hiberno-Saxon art: experiment with forms -- Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum -- Transcript, 1979 June -- (Box 217, Folder 2)
        (Accompanied by correspondence with Barbara Rose regarding images to use for the lecture)
      - On logic and method in art history: from classification to explanation -- New School for Social Research (New York, N.Y.) -- Transcript, 1979 November 17 -- (Box 217, Folder 3)
        (Lecture given at the "Conference on methods in philosophy and the sciences." Accompanied by essay and reprints of Wayne Dynes' writings on Meyer Schapiro and programs. Sound recordings of this lecture can be found in Series VII, Subseries VII.2)
      - Sub-Subseries: III.3.6: 1980s
        - Art studies as an inherently interdisciplinary field -- Barnard College-- Annotated outlines and notes, 1980s (Box 217, Folder 4)
        - The unity of Picasso's art -- Columbia University
        - Lecture I -- Uncorrected transcript, 1980 April (Box 217, Folder 5)
          (Accompanied by research notes)
        - Lecture II -- Annotated transcript, 1980 April (Box 217, Folder 6)
        - Editorial notes, 1980s (Box 217, Folder 7)
          (Accompanied by clippings and research notes chiefly on Picasso's Guernica)
        - Editorial notes and programs, 1980s (Box 217, Folder 8)
          (Notes created by Lillian Milgram Schapiro attempting to reconstruct portions of similar lectures given at Brandeis University and the Albright-Knox Art Gallery for potential publication)
      - On the life and work of Arthur Kingsley Porter -- Harvard University
        (Lecture given at the "Arthur Kingsley Porter centenary symposium on the theme of abstract and rationality in Romanesque art." Sound recordings of this lecture can be found in Series VII, Subseries VII.2)
        - Transcripts, 1983 April 10 (Box 217, Folder 9)
          (Accompanied by notes and programs)
        - Outlines and correspondence 1982-1983 (Box 217, Folder 10)
      - Subseries: III.4: Committees, memberships, and professional affiliations, 1972-1990
        Subseries: III.4 documents Schapiro's professional role as a member in committees and professional affiliations. The subseries is further arranged by area of professional affiliation as follows: Sub-Subseries: III.4.1: Committees, 1972-1978, Sub-Subseries: III.4.2: Memberships, 1969-1989, Sub-Subseries: III.4.3: Professional affiliations, 1989-1990.
        - Sub-Subseries: III.4.1: Committees, 1972-1978
          - The committee to endow a chair in honor of Meyer Schapiro at Columbia University
            - Correspondence, 1972-1978 (Box 218, Folder 1)
            - For Meyer Schapiro: pamphlet, 1974 (Box 218, Folder 2)
              (Pamphlet to promote the limited edition portfolio of prints by twelve artists used to raise funds for the endowment)
            - Reception program and guest list, 1978 (Box 218, Folder 3)
            - Press releases and FAQs, 1972-1978 (Box 218, Folder 4)
            - Articles and clippings, 1972-1978 (Box 218, Folder 5)
        - Sub-Subseries: III.4.2: Memberships, 1969-1989
          - American Artists' Congress -- Membership card, 1939-1940 (Box 218, Folder 6)
          - Board of trustees -- New York Studio School of Drawing, Painting and Sculpture -- Agenda, 1969 (Box 218, Folder 7)
          - American Philosophical Society -- Correspondence and certificate, 1969 (Box 218, Folder 8)
          - National Institute of Arts and Letters (U.S.) -- Programs and clippings, 1976 (Box 218, Folder 9)
          - Fundació Antoni Tàpies -- Correspondence, 1989 (Box 218, Folder 10)
            (Meyer Schapiro served as an Honorary Member of the organization)
        - Sub-Subseries: III.4.3: Professional affiliations, 1989-1990
          - American Academy of Arts and Sciences -- Certificate, 1952 (Box 633, Folder 5)
            (Meyer Schapiro served as a fellow for the organization)
          - Mediaeval Academy of America -- Correspondence and bylaws, 1970 (Box 218, Folder 11)
          - Fondazione Schlesinger -- Correspondence and brochure, 1989 (Box 218, Folder 12)
            (Meyer Schapiro served as an Honorary President for the organization)
          - British Academy -- Correspondence, certificate, and directory, 1990 (Box 218, Folder 13)
            (Meyer Schapiro served a Corresponding Fellow for the organization)
- Series IV: Writings
  This series houses all of Schapiro's writings, from published articles, books, and reviews, to unpublished manuscripts, essays, and translations. For writings that were published during Schapiro's lifetime, the 1995 publication Meyer Schapiro: the bibliography compiled by Lillian Milgram Schapiro was used throughout this series for consistency and to source where articles and reviews first appeared. Information relating to all material published posthumously and that post-dates the 1995 bibliography were retrieved from the archival material itself.
  - Subseries: IV.1: Administrative records, 1960s-2003
    Files in this subseries contain records that aided in the administrative management of Schapiro's writings. The bulk of this material comprises lists of published and unpublished writings.
    - Bibliographies, 1960s (Box 219, Folder 1)
    - Unpublished writings -- Lists, 1970s (Box 219, Folder 2)
    - Published writings -- Lists and notes, 1970s-1980s (Box 219, Folder 3)
    - Published writings -- Correspondence and notes, 1979 (Box 219, Folder 4)
    - Bibliographies, 1980s (Box 219, Folder 5)
    - Literary executorships -- Notes, 1983-1990s (Box 219, Folder 6)
    - Published books -- List, 1985 (Box 219, Folder 7)
    - Unpublished books --List, 1985 (Box 219, Folder 8)
    - Literary executorships -- Drafts, notes, and correspondence, 1980s (Box 219, Folder 9)
    - Unpublished writings -- Notes, 1980s-1990s (Box 219, Folder 10)
    - Unpublished writings -- List, 1990, (2 Folders) (Box 657, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Unpublished writings-- Lists, 1990s, (2 Folders) (Box 657, Folder 3 to 4)
      (Compiled by Lillian Milgram Schapiro)
    - Works released after published bibliography -- List, circa 2003 (Box 657, Folder 5)
  - Subseries: IV.2: Articles, 1929-1994
    Schapiro began publishing articles focused on art and architecture as early as 1929, the year he completed his doctoral dissertation. By 1931, the journal Art Bulletin published parts of his dissertation "The Romanesque Sculpture of Moissac." Since those early years, Schapiro continually published articles in newspapers, journals, and other serials throughout his life. This subseries contains only those articles that have been published, for unpublished works, consult Subseries: IV.3: Essays, Subseries: IV.4: Manuscripts, and Subseries: IV.8: Translations and Poetry in this series. For publications, consult Subseries: IV.5: Publications.
    All bibliographic information in this subseries was retrieved from Lillian Milgram Schapiro's 1995 publication Meyer Schapiro: the bibliography published by George Braziller Inc. Bibliographic information is provided for an article's original publication, consult the published bibliography for information on reprinted versions.
    To facilitate the discovery of records, this subseries is arranged chronologically by decade as follows: Sub-Subseries: IV.2.1: 1929-1930s, Sub-Subseries: IV.2.2: 1940s, Sub-Subseries: IV.2.3: 1950s, Sub-Subseries: IV.2.4: 1960s, Sub-Subseries: IV.2.5: 1970s, Sub-Subseries: IV.2.6: 1980s.
    - Sub-Subseries: IV.2.1: 1929-1930s
      - "The south transept portal of Saint-Sernin in Toulouse" -- Draft typescript and notes, 1929 -- (Box 220, Folder 1)
        (In Parnassus 1, no. 3 (1929): 22-23)
      - "Art" -- Typescript and notes, circa 1930s -- (Box 220, Folder 2)
        (In Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences. New York: Macmillan)
      - "The Romanesque sculpture of Moissac" --
        (Revisions of doctoral dissertation. In Art Bulletin 13, no. 3 (September 1931): 249-352, and no. 4 (December 1931): 464-531)
        - Typescripts and notes, 1931 (Box 220, Folder 3)
        - Typescripts, 1931 (Box 220, Folder 4)
          (Typescripts chiefly on Moissac porch reliefs. Correspond to pages 178-222 of dissertation)
        - Illustration lists, 1931 (Box 220, Folder 5)
        - Annotated typescript, 1931 (Box 220, Folder 6)
          (Typescript paginated 1-109)
        - Annotated typescript, 1931 (Box 220, Folder 7)
          (Typescript paginated 110-221)
      - "Engels on Goethe" -- Annotated typescript, 1932 (Box 220, Folder 8)
        (In New Masses, September 1932 13-14)
      - "Matisse and Impressionism -- Annotated typescript, 1932 -- (Box 220, Folder 9)
        (In Androcles (Columbia College, New York) 1, no. 1 (February 1932): 21-36. Accompanied by annotated photocopy of article. Typescript was created in 1992)
      - "Architects and the crisis: an open letter to the architects, draughtsman, and technicians of America" -- Editorial notes and clippings, 1932 (Box 220, Folder 10)
        (Published in a pamphlet created by the Architects' Committee of League of Professional Groups for Foster and Ford)
      - "Pottery" -- Annotated typescript, correspondence, and research notes, 1934 (Box 220, Folder 11)
        (In Encyclopedia of the Social Science 12: 280-283. New York: Macmillan: 1934)
      - "Taste" -- Annotated typescript, correspondence, and research notes, 1934, (2 Folders) (Box 220, Folder 12 to 13)
        (In Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences, 14: 523-525. New York: Macmillan, 1934)
      - "New documents on St.-Gilles" -- Annotated typescript, correspondence, research notes, and annotated reprints 1935 (Box 220, Folder 14)
        (In Art Bulletin 17, no. 4 (December 1935): 414-431)
      - "Race, nationality and art"
        (In Art Front 2 (March 1936): 10-12)
        - Typescript and notes, 1936 (Box 658, Folder 1)
        - Typescript and clipping, 1936 (Box 658, Folder 2)
          (Photocopy of typescript prepared in 1998)
        - Research notes, 1936, (3 Folders) (Box 658, Folder 3 to 5)
        - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 658, Folder 6)
        - Publication, 1936 (Box 658, Folder 7)
      - "Social bases of art"
        (In American Artists Congress, New York, Proceedings, no. 1 (1936): 31-37)
        - Typescript and research notes, 1936 (Box 658, Folder 8)
        - Proof and clipping, 1936 (Box 658, Folder 9)
      - "The public use of art" -- Annotated clipping and editorial note, 1936 (Box 221, Folder 1)
        (In Art Front 2 (November 1936): 4-6)
      - "Further documents on St.-Gilles" -- Typescript, annotated reprint, research notes, and correspondence, 1937 (Box 221, Folder 2)
        (In Art Bulletin 19, no. 1 (March 1937): 111-112)
      - "From Mozarabic to Romanesque in Silos "
        (In Art Bulletin 21 no. 4 (December 1939): 313-374)
        - Annotated typescript, 1939 (Box 221, Folder 3)
        - Footnotes and corrections, 1939 (Box 221, Folder 4)
        - Proofs and annotated reprints, 1939 (Box 221, Folder 5)
        - Correspondence, 1939-1940 (Box 221, Folder 6)
          (Correspondence chiefly with the Toledo Museum of Art)
      - "The sculpture of Souillac" -- Annotated typescript, correspondence, and research notes 1939 (Box 221, Folder 7)
        (In Mediaeval Studies in Memory of A. Kingsley Porter, ed. W. R. W. Koehler, 359-387. Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1939)
    - Sub-Subseries: IV.2.2: 1940s
      - "The Carolingian copy of the calendar of 354" --
        (In Art Bulletin 22, no. 4 (December 1940): 270-272
        - Annotated typescript, correspondence, and annotated reprint, 1940 (Box 221, Folder 8)
        - Annotated proof and research notes, 1940 (Box 221, Folder 9)
      - "Courbet and popular imagery: an essay on realism and naiveté" --
        (In Journal of the Warburg and Courtauld Institutes 4, no. 3-4 (1940-1941): 164-191)
        - Annotated typescript, 1940 (Box 221, Folder 10)
        - Annotated outlines and notes, 1940 (Box 221, Folder 11)
      - "A note on the inscription of the cathedral of Santiago de Compostela" -- Annotated typescript and research notes, 1942 (Box 221, Folder 12)
        (In Speculum 17, no. 2 (April 1942): 261-264
      - "Cain's jaw-bone that did the first murder" -- Annotated typescript, correspondence, research notes, and annotated reprint, 1942 (Box 222, Folder 1)
        (In Art Bulletin 24, no. 3 (September 1942): 205-212)
      - "The image of the disappearing Christ, the ascension in English art around the year 1000" -- Typescript, correspondence, research notes, and annotated reprint, 1943 (Box 222, Folder 2)
        (In Gazette des Beaux-Arts 23 (March 1943): 135-152)
      - "The angel with the ram in Abraham's Sacrifice: a parallel in Western and Islamic art"
        (In Ars Islamica 10, no. 1-2 (1943): 134-147)
        - Annotated typescript, research notes, correspondence and reprints, 1943 (Box 659, Folder 1)
        - Correspondence and reprints, 1943 (Box 659, Folder 2)
      - "The religious meaning of the Ruthwell Cross"
        (In Art Bulletin 24, no. 4 (December 1944): 242-245)
        - Annotated typescripts, research notes, revisions, and annotated reprint, 1944-1963 (Box 659, Folder 3)
        - Research notes, 1940s-1960s, (3 Folders) (Box 659, Folder 4 to 6)
        - Correspondence, 1944-1963 (Box 659, Folder 7)
      - "The myth of Oedipus" -- Annotated typescripts, 1944 (Box 222, Folder 3)
        (In The Myth of Oedipus with Six Original Etchings by Kurt Seligmann, 9-18. New York: Durlacher Bros.-R. Kirk Askew, Jr., 1944)
      - "A note on Max Weber's politics" -- Annotated typescript and research notes, 1945 (Box 222, Folder 4)
        (In Politics 2, no. 2 (February 1945): 44-48)
      - "'Muscipula Diaboli,' the symbolism of the Mérode altarpiece"
        (In Art Bulletin 27, no. 3 (September 1945): 182-187)
        - Annotated typescript, correspondence, proofs, research notes, and annotated clippings, 1945 (Box 222, Folder 5)
        - Annotated typescript, 1945 (Box 222, Folder 6)
        - Research notes and correspondence, 1945 (Box 222, Folder 7)
      - "On a painting of Van Gogh: crows in the wheat field" -- Annotated typescript, correspondence, and annotated reprints, 1946 (Box 222, Folder 8)
        (In View, Fall 1946 8-14)
      - "A note on 'The Open City': some comments on Farrel's review" -- Annotated typescript, correspondence, research notes, and clippings, 1946 (Box 222, Folder 9)
        (In New International 12 no. 10 (December 1946): 311-313)
      - "On the aesthetic attitude in Romanesque art" -- Annotated typescript, correspondence, and research notes, 1947-1948 (Box 222, Folder 10)
        (In Art and Thought: Essays in Honour of A.K. Coomaraswamy, 130-150. London: Luzac and Co., 1947)
      - "A Life Roundtable on modern art" -- Transcripts, correspondence, and research notes, 1948 (Box 223, Folder 1)
        (In Life, October 11, 1948 58-59)
      - "Fromentin as a critic" -- Research notes and corrections, 1949-1963 (Box 223, Folder 2)
        (In Partisan Review 16, no. 1 (January 1949): 25-51)
      - "The place of the Joshua Roll in Byzantine history" -- Annotated reprint, research notes, and correspondence, 1946-1949 (Box 223, Folder 3)
        (In Gazette des Beaux-Arts 35 (March 1949): 161-176). Originally a paper presented at the Premier Congrès International Byzantino-Slave et Oriental, New York, April 28, 1946)
    - Sub-Subseries: IV.2.3: 1950s
      - "Essay in Symposium, Religion and the Intellectuals" -- Typescript, proof, clipping, 1950 (Box 223, Folder 4)
        (In Partisan Review 17, no. 4 (April 1950): 331-339)
      - "The Joseph scenes on the Maximianus Throne in Ravenna" -- Annotated typescript, correspondence, research notes, and annotated clipping, 1950-1952 (Box 223, Folder 5)
        (In Gazeete de Beaux-Arts 40 (July 1952): 27-38)
      - "Rebellion in art: [The Armory Show]"
        (In America in Crisis, ed. Daniel Aaron, 202-242. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1952)
        - Typescript, 1952 (Box 223, Folder 6)
        - Research notes and correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 223, Folder 7)